<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact account of the late action at the town of Dundalk against the Irish by Their Majesties forces commanded by Sir John Lanier : together with the articles of the surrender of Moss-Town.</title>
            <author>J. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W53</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R235777</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07915907</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07915907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1218:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact account of the late action at the town of Dundalk against the Irish by Their Majesties forces commanded by Sir John Lanier : together with the articles of the surrender of Moss-Town.</title>
                  <author>J. W.</author>
                  <author>Nugent, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Greenhills,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Account signed: J.W.</note>
                  <note>Articles of surrender signed: William Nugent.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An EXACT ACCOUNT OF <hi>The Late Action</hi> AT THE Town of DUNDALK, AGAINST The <hi>IRISH,</hi> by Their MAJESTIES FORCES, Commanded by Sir <hi>JOHN LANIER.</hi> TOGETHER, With the ARTICLES of the Surrender of <hi>MOSS-TOWN.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Lisbourne</hi> 
                     <date>the 10th of <hi>February,</hi> 1689/90.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>ON <hi>Friday</hi> his Grace received an Expreſs, that the Forces he ſent from <hi>Antrim</hi> to <hi>Charlemont,</hi> had Burnt many of their Boats, and Fired the Bridge, half of which was Burnt down before the Enemy could extinguiſh it; and a very hot Diſpute hapned, in which we loſt a <hi>French</hi> Captain in the Regiment of <hi>Cukimott,</hi> and five or ſix private Souldiers, with the loſs of many on the Enemies ſide, and ſome Priſoners.</p>
               <p>The ſame Evening his Grace received an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs from the <hi>Newry,</hi> that there were ſix Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of the Enemies Horſe, and five Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Foot arrived at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and that five Regiments more of Foot were coming to them; and that ſeveral Gabbard (or Lighters) Loads of Hay and Oats were arrived there from <hi>Droghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yeſtarday another Expreſs from the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> That there were come to <hi>Dundalk</hi> 13 or 14 Gabbards more from <hi>Droghedah,</hi> loaden with Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Cheeſe, Butter, and the like.</p>
               <p>Upon which his Grace hath ſent Expreſſes to Col. <hi>Stewart</hi> and Col. <hi>Purſell,</hi> to direct them in the better ſecuring the <hi>Newry,</hi> and adjacent Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, and another to the Captain of the Man of War in <hi>Carrickfergus</hi> Road (as is thought) to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch ſome Perſons to burn the Hay, Oats, Gab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And alſo by a Meſſenger arrived here four days ſince, he hath ſent for the <hi>Danes</hi> to haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en thither; and to Morrow deſigns towards the <hi>Newry</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Febr.</hi> 13. On <hi>Tueſday</hi> the General ſet out from hence towards the <hi>Newry,</hi> having firſt given Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for all our Forces to diſpatch from all Parts towards him, and given out 6000 Arms to the Country to defend themſelves in their abſence; and accordingly our Forces were on their march.</p>
               <p>But this Morning his Grace ſent an Expreſs from <hi>Drummore,</hi> that the whole Noiſe was a falſe Alarm; and order'd Directions to be ſent to all Regiments to ſtop their march, and return to their Quarters.</p>
               <p>In my laſt I told you, our General was gone towards <hi>Newry,</hi> but by the Road receiving an Account, which contradicted his former, of the Enem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeedy approaches towards our Fronti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s on that Quarter; his Grace went no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>Drummore,</hi> eight Miles from this place, where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave Orders for all the Forces on their March to thoſe parts, to return to their Quarters, excepting 500 Foot, and 500 Horſe and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, who were detached out of ſeveral Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Commanded by Sir <hi>John Lanier,</hi> to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> where they arrived on <hi>Friday</hi> Morning the 14th. before day, and paſſed the River a Mile above the Town, near <hi>Bellews-Caſtle,</hi> where being a Garriſon of the Enemy, as our Men approached, the Enemy fired briskly, and ours as briskly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced upon them; the Enemy fled from the Walls into the Caſtle, and upon this briskly fired from the Battlements; however, our Men, like Lions eager for a Prey, could not be daunted or reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ran up to the Gate, which being only Barricadoed within, was ſoon forced open, and our Men ſoon got into the lower part of the Houſe, and fell to firing up through the Floor, by which they wounded one Man, and threatning to burn the Houſe, the Enemy from above hung down a white Handkerchief, and deſired leave to march out with their Arms; but being denied that, were forced to accept of Quarter, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render themſelves up Priſoners, of which there is in all about twenty of their Army, and ten Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Fellows, who are now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Road coming hither under a Guard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Caſtle, another Party advanced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Enemy's ſide of the Town <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the South Eaſt part, where our chief Works formerly were, and
<pb facs="tcp:40399:2"/>without Oppoſition burnt all the Houſes on that Quarter to the Gate, where a ſtrong Party being got, oppoſed our further Progreſs, till in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt we loſt one Lieutenant, and two private Men, and killed one of the Enemy, and then retired.</p>
               <p>There were other ways which with difficulty our Forces might have (yet not without great difficulty) attempted to enter the Town; but there being 3000 of the Enemy within, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſtrong Caſtles and Houſes; and not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a ſtronger Party might advance from <hi>Atherdee,</hi> where ſome of their Horſe lieth, it was thought adviſable to retire, which accordingly our Men did, to the Fields and adjacent Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, from whence they brought 1500 Head of Cattle, without the leaſt oppoſition from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; which at the <hi>Newry</hi> is to be divided among the whole Party.</p>
               <p>All the Houſes they burnt were full of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, ſo that it's believed, and the Priſoners report that the Town is full alſo: Our Men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd four Gibbards, in the River of <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and a Ship of ours lying at the Harbours mouth, who, it's ſaid, have burnt four others there loaden with Forage from <hi>Dublin.</hi> Our Out-Scouts lye conſtantly within four Miles of <hi>Dundalk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The General returned hither on <hi>Saturday,</hi> and at Night received Colonel <hi>Wolſely</hi>'s Letter, and which Action will undoubtedly much fruſtrate the Enemies deſigned Expectations, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard their intentions of Attacking us in our Quarters, as without all-doubt they intended by all theſe great Preparations.</p>
               <p>I have herewith ſent you the Articles on which the brave Lady therein mentioned, ſurrendred up her Houſe to the Brigadeer <hi>Nugent,</hi> who, we are told, is mortally wounded in that brave Action on the 11th Inſtant, by 1000 <hi>Inniskilling Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> Commanded by the famous Col. <hi>Wooſely,</hi> in which they fought 4000 cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <hi>Iriſh,</hi> under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> at <hi>Cavan,</hi> whom they routed twice, kill'd 300, took many Priſoners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of which you will have the full Particulars this Poſt from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I am yours,</hi> J. W.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conditions granted by the Honourable <hi>William Nugent,</hi> one of his Majeſties Brigadeers, and Lord-Lieutenant of the County of <hi>Longford;</hi> To all Perſons reſiding in <hi>Moſs-Town,</hi> upon the Surrender of the ſaid Houſe, Fire-Arms, and Ammunition.</head>
               <p n="1">I. That <hi>Sarah</hi> Lady <hi>Newcomen</hi> be at her Choice, either to ſtay in her own Houſe, and there peaceably and quietly to enjoy all the Goods now in her Poſſeſſion belonging to Herſelf, Children, or Relations; or elſe to remove Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Family, and the aforeſaid Goods, to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever place her Ladyſhip ſhall appoint and that the ſaid Lady ſhall be permitted to keep her Chaplain Mr. <hi>John Wilſon,</hi> to officiate for her in her own Houſe, if her Ladyſhip ſtays there, or in her Journey if ſhe removes.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That the ſaid Houſe of <hi>Moſs Town</hi> ſhall not be burnt by any Party of Men to be placed there.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That all Perſons now in the Houſe, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly belonging to it, who are ſo inclin'd, have liberty to March ſafely from thence, with their Lives, carrying all Swords and Horſes not Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, and Goods now in their Poſſeſſion, to <hi>Inniskilling,</hi> or to whatever place the ſaid Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons belonging to the ſaid Houſe, ſhall think convenient, with a ſafe Convoy under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Captain <hi>Francis Nangle,</hi> and Captain <hi>Bryan Mac Mahone,</hi> to defend the ſaid Lady <hi>Newcomen,</hi> and all Perſons belonging to the ſaid Houſe, from the Injury of all Perſons in their Journey.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. That all Perſons impriſoned either for being in this Houſe, or coming hither, that are now in <hi>Longford,</hi> be Releaſed, and have leave to march with the reſt of the Party, to the place they ſhall appoint.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That Perſons who have deſerted His Majeſty's Army, and are now in the ſaid Houſe, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>Charles Deanes,</hi> ſhall have Liberty to March with their Lives and Goods with the reſt of the Men.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. That the Lady <hi>Newcomen,</hi> and all other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the ſaid Houſe, have Liberty to carry what Proviſions they think convenient with them, and alſo liberty to diſpoſe of all the reſt of their Proviſions, Corn, and Goods, as they think fit.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. That all ſuch as are inclin'd to ſtay in the Country, or elſewhere, ſhall have free and full Pardon for all paſt Crimes; and a Protection for them and Goods for the future againſt all Perſons: and that protected Perſons ſhall have liberty to carry their Goods to their reſpective Habitations.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. That the Convoy ſhall be ready at 24 hours warning, under the Command of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Perſon, to Convoy the ſaid Lady, and all Perſons in her Houſe, to the place where they ſhall appoint.</p>
               <p>And that theſe above-mentioned Conditions be juſtly performed, I do hereby Oblige my ſelf, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Hand and Seal, this <hi>13th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1689.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Nugent.</signed>

                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Licensd,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>March 1. 1690.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do hereby empower all Officers and Souldiers to Preſs in this Journey for all ſuch belonging to the ſaid Houſe of <hi>Moſs-town,</hi> as will pay <hi>12 <abbr>d.</abbr> per</hi> day for each Horſe ſo Preſt, to carry them, their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Goods. And I do hereby Promiſe to take no Advantage of any Error committed in the wording of the ſaid Conditions, but admit them to be taken in the largeſt ſenſe, to the Advantage and Aſſurance of thoſe to whom they appertain. As Witneſs my Hand this <hi>13th.</hi> of <hi>January, 1689.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>William Nugent.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Greenhill,</hi> near the <hi>Exchange.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
